Mert Onur Cakiroglu

PHD STUDENT · COMPUTER SCIENCE

Indiana University, Luddy School of Informatics, Computing, and Engineering 700 N Woodlawn Ave, Bloomington, IN 47408

■ meocakir@iu.edu | 🎢 mert.it.com | 🖸 Lumpus99 | 🛅 mert-onur-cakiroglu

Research Interests

My research focuses on the intersection of machine learning, temporal data, video learning, and representation learning. I develop advanced models to improve video understanding, particularly in compressed domains and through self-supervised techniques. Additionally, I explore novel methods for representing low-dimensional sequential data, such as protein sequences and univariate time series, using de Bruijn graphs to enhance model performance in classification and forecasting tasks.

Education _____

Indiana University, Luddy School of Informatics, Computing, and Engineering

Bloomington, Indiana Fall 2023 – present

PHD COMPUTER SCIENCE

Advisor: Prof. Dr. Mehmet M Dalkilic
 Co-Advisor: Dr. Hasan Kurban

TOBB University of Economics and Technology

BS COMPUTER SCIENCE

Ankara, Turkey 2017 – 2021

Publications _____

PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Mert Onur Cakiroglu, Hasan Kurban, Elham Khorasani Buxton, Mehmet Dalkilic (2024). *A Novel Discrete Time Series Representation with De Bruijn Graphs for Enhanced Forecasting Using TimesNet* (Extended Abstract). IEEE International Conference on Data Science and Advanced Analytics (DSAA 2024) - Machine Learning Journal Track

PEER REVIEWED JOURNALS

Mert Onur Cakiroglu, Hasan Kurban, Parichit Sharma, M. Oguzhan Kulekci, Elham Khorasani Buxton, Maryam Raeeszadeh-Sarmazdeh, Mehmet Dalkilic (2024). *An Extended De Bruijn Graph for Feature Engineering Over Biological Sequential Data*. Machine Learning Journal

Mert Onur Cakiroglu, Hasan Kurban, Elham Khorasani Buxton, Mehmet Dalkilic (2024). *A Novel Discrete Time Series Representation with De Bruijn Graphs for Enhanced Forecasting Using TimesNet. Machine Learning: Science and Technology* (Under Review)

Mert Onur Cakiroglu, Hasan Kurban, Elham Khorasani Buxton, Mehmet Dalkilic (2024). *A Reinforcement Learning Approach* to Effective Forecasting of Pediatric Hypoglycemia in Diabetes I Patients: an extended de Bruijn Graph. Nature – Scientific Reports (Under Review)

Research Experience

Texas A&M University at Qatar - Temporary Research Associate

Doha, Qatar

Advisor: Dr. Hasan Kurban

May. 2024 - Jul. 2024

- Developing a self-supervised learning framework for video data, enabling the model to learn meaningful representations without labeled data, improving video understanding tasks such as classification and segmentation.
- Implementing federated video learning in the compressed domain, optimizing the model's performance while preserving user privacy and reducing communication overhead in distributed learning environments.

Student Researcher - Kurban Intelligence Labs

Advisor: Dr. Hasan Kurban

Aug. 2023 – Ongoing

• Machine Learning Research
Conducting research on video learning, self-supervised learning, and representation learning with de Bruijn graphs.

Laboratory Website: kurbanintelligencelab.com

Awards and Recognition _	

2023 Fall 2023 Luddy Doctoral Associate Instructor Fellowship, Luddy School of Informatics, Computing, and Engineering